Thank you.
I'm with Corey Smith, and I have the distinct honor.
I'm not sure what got into Ryan's pants, but he let me do Palm Sunday.
So it's my distinct honor and privilege to bring you this year's Palm Sunday Sermon.
If you've been participating with, in the lentil season with brothers and sisters around the globe,
we talked about today, big day, right?
Today marks the start of this year's Holy Week.
It's every year, the beginning of Holy Week is marked by today, Palm Sunday.
And we're going to, you may have guessed it, we're going to talk about Jesus' triumphant entry into Jerusalem.
Today gets its names from what?
The palms, the palms, the palms that branches that were laid at the feet of Jesus and even waved in the air as he was welcomed into Jerusalem on the back of a donkey.
And our kids did a fantastic job with that today.
But I wanted to take this opportunity.
My wife has a constant reminder of, you need to unpack that a little bit more.
So I want to take this opportunity before we get started to unpack some of Holy Week.
Because we really, a lot of us won't see each other again in corporate service until Resurrection Sunday.
So I want to take this time to kind of unpack that.
So, Scott, if you want to go to the next one for me.
I wanted to explain this to you guys because a lot of you may not have grown up in church.
Or you may have grown up in a church tradition that didn't put a ton of emphasis on Holy Week.
So this whole thing might be new to you.
So I want to say, first off, we're glad you're here and you're more than welcome to be here with us.
And I just want to give you the Cliff Notes version so that you're well informed.
Sound good?
So tomorrow will be Holy Monday.
So this is the day that the church historically celebrates Jesus' cleansing of the temple.
And not like with Lysol and a swore for wet jet.
But like clearing out the money changers and those selling animals for sacrifices.
Those people that made God's house a den of thieves according to Jesus.
If you recall last week, Ryan dropped that kind of inner working of the dynamic of the chief priest
and the scribes.
Remember that?
So one being an agent of the temple, keeping everything just so right that the temple leaders
retained their political and religious authority over, lined in their own pockets, right?
Power as well.
And then we have the other side, the moral agent, making sure people acted just so right
that Messiah would come, right?
We get, we understand that dynamic a little bit better and Ryan set it up perfect for this
week.
So today we'll read, our text will be Matthew and we'll, we'll talk about Jesus' triumphant
entry.
And Matthew, Matthew's text kind of relays it like this happens one after another.
So today it's like a Palm Sunday, Holy Monday combo.
So you guys are getting like a two for one.
But traditionally the church history celebrates the cleansing of the temple on Monday.
And the gospel of Mark records Jesus as walking into the temple, looking around, and then
going back to Bethany with his friends before coming back to cleanse the temple on Monday.
More of that to come.
Tuesday, on Holy Tuesday, we'll see Jesus leave the city in the late afternoon with his
disciples and go to the Mount of Olives, which sits directly, if you're like a geography
person, which sits directly east of the temple and overlooks Jerusalem.
The tumultuous events of Tuesday are sometimes referred to the Olivet Discourse because Jesus
kind of unpacks everything on the Mount of Olives that's going on.
But before that, what happens leading up to Jesus kind of leading, going to the Mount of Olives,
the religious leaders are upset at Jesus for establishing himself as a moral authority, or
a spiritual authority, I'm sorry.
They planned an ambush with the intent to place Jesus under arrest, but Jesus hits them with
harsh judgment in Matthew 23 saying, blind guides, this is some like serious roast.
I was talking to my brother-in-law the other day.
It's like Jesus is like, got these roasts planned and he's just hitting them with it.
Blind guides, for you are like whitewashed tombs, beautiful on the outside, but filled on
the inside with dead people's bones and all sorts of impurity.
Outwardly, you look like righteous people, but inwardly, your hearts are filled with hypocrisy
and lawlessness.
Snakes, son of vipers, how will you escape the judgment of hell?
And then we come to Spy Wednesday.
In the case of Spy Wednesday, the wording means exactly what you think it means.
Today is the remembrance of Judas' actions in Matthew 26, 14 through 16, if you want to
look that up.
But I've got it here.
Then went one of the twelve, who was called Judas Iscariot, to the chief priest and said
to them, what will you give me?
And I will deliver him unto you.
But they appointed him 30 pieces of silver, and from thenceforth he sought an opportunity
to betray Jesus.
If you participated in our Practicing the Way small groups, you've probably learned through
our fasting series that this is why some of the early church fasted on Wednesdays.
That idea to mourn Jesus betraying God incarnate in flesh.
Then we get to Maundy Thursday.
This is a good one, right?
This is not a typo for Monday, Thursday.
But Maundy, which is not used, we don't use this in our vocabulary, right?
But Maundy comes from the old French word, Mandae, or Maundy, and in turn, Mandatum, which
means to mandate or command.
Maundy Thursday is the day Jesus would have partaken in the Jewish feast of Passover, and
he washed his disciples' feet.
And in John 13, 34, Jesus says this, I give you a new command, right, mandate, love one
another, just as I have loved you, you are to love one another.
This language of new command in the Latin Vulgate is Novum Mandatum, or Maundy.
So when you hear Maundy Thursday, think Mandate Thursday, what did Jesus command us to do?
Love one another.
Then we come to Good Friday, the trial, the crucifixion, the death, and burial of Jesus.
Good Friday is the most difficult and revered and mournful day of Holy Week.
The same city that welcomed Jesus on Sunday with shouts of Hosanna now shouted out, give us Barabbas,
a common criminal.
They shouted, crucify him.
When they knew, when the people knew how shameful, painful, and agonizing Roman crucifixion was,
right, this was not a, this was not something that they were unattached from.
They probably had family members that may have been tortured under Roman persecution, and now
they're giving Jesus over to that.
They all shared some experience of a loved one being oppressed by Roman brutality.
Now that city, now that, now, now that's the city that Jesus weeped over in previous to that.
The same city now hands him over to the brutality of Rome.
This is the day where Jesus experiences humanity's darkest brokenness.
But Jesus still prescribes a prayer over them, and it still prescribes a prayer over us.
Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.
The early church not only fasted on Wednesdays to mourn the betrayal of Jesus, but also on Fridays
to mourn the death of Jesus on Good Friday.
Then we come to Silent Saturday, the day where Jesus' body laid in the tomb, guarded by Roman
soldiers throughout this day on Saturday, which was the Shabbat or the Sabbath for the Jewish
people.
While his body laid in the tomb, we remember on Silent Saturday the days it was quiet, the
days where it seemed like all hope was lost.
Jesus has been taken away from us.
Meanwhile, counter to our thoughts and expectations, hope, true hope was being reclaimed.
He was conquering death, both spiritually and physically, securing our eternal salvation.
1 Peter 1, 18-19 records,
For you know that God paid a ransom to save you from the empty life you inherited from your
ancestors.
And the ransom he paid was not mere gold or silver.
He paid for you with the precious lifeblood of Christ, the sinless, spotless Lamb of God.
And then we come to, last but certainly not least, Resurrection Sunday, my favorite thing to talk
about.
Resurrection Sunday is where we reach the culmination of Holy Week.
The resurrection of Jesus is the most important event in all of the Christian faith.
It is the very foundation of any Christian doctrine, and it all hinges on the truth of this account
in history.
I won't, I thought about this, I will not steal Pastor Ryan's thunder, but this is the day,
this is the feast.
See, we talked about fasting on Wednesdays and Fridays, and we do that because we understand
the feast is coming.
But why is the fast worth it?
Because the feast of Jesus returning will make us all, forget all about the hunger that we
experienced while he was away.
Amen?
So today, we're back at the beginning of Holy Week, Palm Sunday.
Does everybody feel like they have a better grasp on Holy Week now?
Good.
That's what, that was my goal.
But what's in a name, Palm Sunday?
That's kind of the theme of my sermon today, if you will.
And we've unpacked Holy Week a little bit more, so let's unpack Palm Sunday.
Sound good?
You guys didn't have a choice in it.
I love that joke, because it's true.
Like, we're going there.
But you guys know I love some good context, right?
I typically start out my sermons giving you the context so you can immerse yourself kind
of where we're at, what the people may have been experiencing, and kind of get the wheels
turning outside of the 21st American context of that, right?
So, some ideas to keep with you today.
What could we glean from some deeper contextual meanings around Palm Sunday?
What was the potential mindset of the people who waved those palm branches?
How did these people, this city, go from welcoming their Messiah with shouts of Hosanna to shouting,
give us Barabbas, to shouting crucify him?
Now, with the context of that, I don't necessarily think there's a roving crowd of people going
around yelling these things.
But what I want you to get in the mindset of is what ammunition would the chief priests
and scribes have access to, to get rid of this rabbi from Nazareth, this teacher who disrupts
the order, and who claims himself to be greater than the temple, how could the religious elites
use the people and their expectations to sway a decision?
Expectations are a powerful thing left unchecked.
It's ruined relationships, friendships, marriages.
Think about it.
When I expect this person to do this thing, and they didn't, what's our immediate response?
Is it anger, frustration, retribution?
Are these listed in Galatians 5 as fruits of the Spirit?
They're not.
Could we call them fruit of the flesh?
Today, prayerfully, I hope to take us there and how we might put ourselves in the shoes of
these first century people and how to reflect and recognize some of our own blind spots when
it comes to trusting Jesus for who he is and not who we want him to be.
We good?
If y'all leave, you can.
So last week, Pastor Ryan talked about our agendas behind our actions, right?
Do we have an agenda like the scribes or Pharisees that may look good on the outside, but we've
got a hidden motive or agenda that we're trying to get.
If this God, this Yahweh, this Jesus came in flesh to his creation in the personhood of
Jesus, wouldn't it stand to reason some of the things he says and does would deeply resonate
with the core of who we are and things we love and affirm so easily?
Wouldn't that make sense?
Wouldn't he do things to appeal to the echoes of Eden that still linger in our hearts?
Healing the blind, making the lame to walk.
These signposts that point away, point to the thing, the way things were supposed to
be, not to the thing they are, right?
This Eden, this echoes back to Eden.
But wouldn't it also stand to reason, and we don't like this, I don't like this, so I'm
assuming you guys don't like it.
Wouldn't it also stand to reason that he would confront us with hard truths that would shake
us to our core?
Things so counter to our broken bodies and culture that we need to repent, relent, and turn
to him with our whole selves, because it's so different than our desires or expectations
of how this thing's supposed to work.
Wouldn't he do things as the God and creator of the universe, do things that our moral minds
couldn't comprehend, and things that need conquered and demolished in ways that we never could?
See, Jesus, these are questions I ask.
How does turning the other cheek, caring for the poor, the widow, and the orphan change the
world, especially better than an armed revolt?
How will prayer, fasting, and a sincere heart towards God's will change this world more than
weapons, tanks, or bombs?
Maybe, just maybe, the vengeance is God's, not ours.
How is loving my neighbor as myself fully bring your kingdom into a more clear picture?
How does Jesus' death on the cross and resurrection start a revolution?
A revolution so powerful, so compelling, that here we are, 2,000 years later, still worshiping?
The list goes on, but this is the question I want you to sit with and wrestle with this
week.
What expectations have I put on Jesus that are my own and not something he promised?
Let's pray.
Dear Heavenly Father, in Jesus' name, we ask that you give us ears to hear and hearts to
receive whatever it is in this message that you would have for us.
For those hurting in this room, I pray healing over them.
For those in this room that are anxious, I pray peace over them.
And for those who feel lost in this room, Lord, I pray they find the abundant life that
you share with all of us.
Lord, we thank you for the truths that affirm us to our core, that we are children of God
and who are loved by you, but we ask you to help us wrestle with the things that are divinely
inspired, that so deeply irritate and vex our flesh, that you would help us fully adopt
not our will, but yours for this world.
Lord, may we have eyes to see your kingdom and your kingship, and may we humbly bow in submission
to that reign and rule.
May we not make you in our image, but that you would conform us to yours, that you be
the potter and we be the clay with no expectation of the master's divine plan, but an unswerving
obedience to it.
We pray all of this for your glory and our neighbor's good, and in Jesus' name we pray.
Amen.
I'm going to apologize, I think.
Maybe it's that incense left over from last week.
Today we'll be in Matthew 21, if you guys want to start turning there, but we're going
to still work through some of this context.
As we'll see from our text, the name Palm Sunday comes from the account that palm branches
and coats were laid in the road as citizens of Jerusalem welcomed Jesus into their capital
city.
The account of Jesus' arrival is recorded in all four Gospels.
Matthew 21, Mark 11, John 12, Luke 19.
Today we're going to be focusing on Matthew, but my goal is to give you an overarching hermeneutic,
and that's a $5 word, but an interpretation to help you understand the triumphant entry from
all four varying perspectives.
This overarching theme of the triumphant entry.
There's a lot happening here, from the citizens that are anticipating, to the disciples unknowingly
helping to fulfill prophecy, to the rightful king of the universe returning to Jerusalem.
Today my goal is to focus on that prophetic verse from Kent's reading this morning in Zechariah 9.
Look, your king is coming to you.
This pervasive idea throughout the narrative of Scripture is that Jesus, this incarnate, this
Messiah, God in flesh, has a desire to dwell with mankind.
From the beginning of the garden in Genesis to New Jerusalem in Revelation, God has the desire
to dwell and abide alongside his creation.
If you were here or listened to my John 15 sermon, you'll see some parallels.
And I'll give you the guardrail, right?
I'll make the Iron Man argument.
Not because I'm introducing, this is not a parallel because I don't think I'm introducing them,
but I believe the Bible is an overarching narrative that tells the story of God as creator,
redeemer, and king who wishes to dwell with his creation.
Fully restoring us as his image bearers, and he is our rightful and just king.
To understand what exactly is happening in this passage,
you need to understand the historical context in which this story takes place.
Israel is under Roman occupation and governed politically and religiously by a group of leaders called
the Sanhedrin.
That is, Jewish elites, these guys that were tasked with not disrupting the thinly held peace
with Rome.
We'll keep the status quo.
Rome, you can be in charge.
You let us worship and do things as we want, and we'll kind of keep the peace with the people.
These people, the common people of Israel were looking to the coming of Messiah,
which they had always been told would be a warrior king like David.
Someone who would liberate the nation out from the oppression of Rome and restore the glory of Israel
to what it was like before the exile.
We familiar, remember in our Old Testaments?
So in our Old Testaments, that once the nation of Israel went into exile in Babylon,
it never really left captivity.
It's called the diaspora, another $5 word, or the dispersion.
They went from one oppressive regime to the next, right?
Babylon, the Persians, the Greeks, and now the Romans.
Rome was this oppressive, tyrannical superpower that was now lording over a people.
A people whom God, Yahweh, this Yahweh, has called his children.
And this oppressive structure that's currently Rome, it would need to be dealt with.
The Israelites heard these stories and began to speculate in their minds what Messiah must do.
They heard the narrative of Moses, who confronted Pharaoh through the power of God,
bringing plagues against these wicked Egyptians that kept us in bondage, right?
And Pharaoh finally beat down through the plagues, eventually secedes after the firstborn death of his son
and the death of every firstborn son of the Egyptians.
And this is Thursday, right?
This is Passover, which is at hand, right?
It's this celebration, the celebration that God passed over the Hebrew households
that were covered under the blood of the Lamb.
This is what they're celebrating.
See, the first century Israelites, they knew the story of Joshua,
the military leader who led the armies of Israel
and mercilessly slaughtered the Canaanites to conquer the promised land,
a land which God promised to his people.
They saw the story of the prophet Elijah that called down fire from heaven
and slaughtered the prophets of Baal.
This must be what Messiah is going to do, and this is how he must do it.
Could this, and I'm posing this as a question,
could this be their expectation of who he is and what he has promised?
See, the other side of that coin is this.
You put yourself in the view of a first century Israelite,
something that would have been of the utmost importance is the temple.
So this wonder of the ancient world, I think we give in our mind in 21st century context
that we think of the temple like a church building, like a nice church building.
Like, oh, it was nice for him, everybody went there.
Like, this was a wonder of the ancient world.
This was a huge, magnificent example of the God of the Israelites, right?
If you're a nerd like me and like nerdy history stuff,
like you think of the Parthenon in Greece,
and you think of that's a representation of the gods of Greece, right?
They built that to represent the gods of Greece.
The world would have seen, the secular world,
Rome would have seen the temple as the example of the God of the Israelites, this Yahweh.
But for the Israelites, this temple was the permanent structure or dwelling place
that was built after the portable dwelling place of God,
the tabernacle in the desert.
The tabernacle in the temple was built to represent a place
where God physically dwelt with man, the Garden of Eden.
This was built to hearken back to the original design and the future promise
that in this small but grandiose scale mirrored the Garden of Eden,
the place where heaven meets earth.
See, if you recall from my John 15 sermon,
this is the second temple time period.
And many people believe the glory of God left the temple before the Babylonians,
before the first temple was destroyed by the Babylonians.
The Israelites looked to a prophecy spoken by the prophet Ezekiel five centuries earlier
that talked about the glory of God leaving the temple via the east gate of Jerusalem
due to the rebellion and idolatry of the people and leadership of Israel.
So we're going to look at Ezekiel 10, 18 through 19.
I think we got it up on the screen.
Then the glory of the Lord moved away from the threshold of the temple
and stopped above the cherubim.
And the cherubim lifted their wings and ascended from the earth right before my eyes.
The wheels were beside them as they went.
And the glory of God of Israel was above them.
And it stopped at the entrance to the eastern gate of the Lord's house.
See, from there, the glory went and stopped over the Mount of Olives.
Later in prophetic writings of Ezekiel, it talks about a time where the glory of God
would return from the east to the temple where it would be re-consecrated or cleansed.
Ezekiel 43, he led me to the gate, the one that faces east,
and I saw the glory of God of Israel coming from the east.
And his voice sounded like a roar of a huge torrent,
and the earth shone with his glory.
So the people, the Israelites, looked to their coming Messiah,
the rightful warrior and king,
that the coming of the glory of God would be from the east of Jerusalem.
There's also a prophetic word that the first century Jews held on this time of waiting,
and that was Zechariah 9, 9.
Rejoice greatly, O daughter Zion.
Shout in triumph, daughter Jerusalem.
Look, your king is coming to you, righteous and victorious.
And I want to unpack that word victorious, or having salvation.
Humble and riding on a donkey, on the colt, a foal of a donkey.
See, from Bethany, Jesus and his disciples went to the Mount of Olives east of Jerusalem,
and that's where we're going to pick up our Scripture for today.
Sorry, we had to get there, right?
I've got something I want you to do today because I love the participation factor of the day.
Can we, can you guys get involved?
Can we get involved?
Is that too much to ask from the congregation?
When you see it, we sang the song this morning.
When you see Hosanna in all caps, I want you to shout it out.
And I mean, I want you to shout it out with some conviction, right?
Let's practice.
Hosanna on three.
One, two, three.
Hosanna!
All right.
And because I want you to reflect on the mindset of the people and the meaning of this word,
we sang this this morning and this was on my heart.
Hosanna is our plea, meaning God save us.
When you sang Hosanna, you are singing and shouting, God save us.
Can we do that?
Can we shout it when we're reading it?
Also, because I, if you're able to, let's stand as we read the word of the Lord this morning.
Matthew 21.
When they approached Jerusalem and came to Bethlehem at the Mount of Olives,
Jesus then sent two disciples telling them,
Go into the village ahead of you.
At once you will find a donkey tied there with her colt.
Untie them and bring them to me.
If anyone says anything to you, say that the Lord needs them.
And he will send them at once.
This took place so that when it was spoken,
what was spoken through the prophet might be fulfilled.
Tell daughter Zion, see, your king is coming to you gentle
and mounted on a donkey, on a colt, on the foal of a donkey.
The disciples went and did just as Jesus directed them.
They brought the donkey and the colt and they laid their clothes on him
and he sat on them.
A very large crowd spreading their clothes on the road.
Others were cutting branches from the trees, spreading them on the road.
Then the crowds who went ahead of him and those who followed shouted,
Hosanna.
I messed up.
Y'all did great.
To the son of David.
Blessed is he who comes in the name of the Lord.
In the highest heaven.
When he entered Jerusalem, the whole city was in an uproar saying,
Who is this?
The crowds were saying,
This is the prophet Jesus from Nazareth of Galilee.
Verse 12.
Jesus went into the temple and threw out all those buying and selling
and he overturned the tables of the money changers and those selling of doves.
He said to them,
It is written,
My house will be called a house of prayer, but you are making it a den of thieves.
The blind and the lame came to him in the temple and he healed them.
When the chief priests and scribes saw the wonders that he did and the children shouting in the temple,
Hosanna.
And they said to the son of David, they were indignant.
And they said to him,
Do you hear what these children are saying?
Jesus replied,
Have you never read?
You have prepared praise from the mouth of infants and nursing babies.
Then he left them and he went to the city of Bethany and spent the night there.
This is the word of the Lord.
You guys may be seated.
So with the proclamation of the Lord in need of a donkey and riding into Jerusalem from the east,
you can imagine, you can tangibly feel the excitement from the Israelites, right?
This is the expectation that's building.
Here's this prophet, this rabbi, this person who claims himself to be greater than the temple,
fulfilling prophecies, preaching that the kingdom of God is near,
causing the blind and lame to see, the deaf to hear.
Here he is riding on a donkey from the east, just as the prophet Ezekiel had promised,
coming into the city like the flesh and blood ark of the covenant.
That's where the glory of God dwelt, if you didn't know that.
But with his disciples, just like King David.
So the people, overcome by joy, take their jackets off to lay them in the street.
They cut down palm branches to squelch the dust.
This is all to welcome their king, their Messiah, and their Savior back home with his people.
So I think in our 21st century context,
the motif of laying down jackets for a king might be removed from our culture,
but I think it's something we can grasp, right?
We can figure that out.
I mean, imagine, the road's dusty or muddy.
If you live in West Virginia, you're probably used to that.
We'd cover the road for Caesar.
We're obviously going to cover it for Jesus.
Cover it for Messiah.
But the palm branches, though.
It seems like there might be a cultural meaning that we're missing in our 21st century American context.
And if you do some exploring, there's no real clear evidence in the Old Testament for why the people would do this.
Or at least a clue as to why.
So the temptation there is to see it as a one-off event or just read over it and it's Palm Sunday.
No big deal.
But I think that we miss a large puzzle piece to Holy Week.
See, Jesus is doing what Jesus does best.
He's flipping the script.
This idea of, and we've heard Jesus say this,
you have heard it said, but I say unto you.
There's two accounts of palm leaves being used by the Israelites in the Jewish Apocrypha,
which is not typically in your Protestant Bibles.
But it's in 1st and 2nd Maccabees.
Could this be an indicator of prophetic expectation of the people?
Let's read those together.
1st Maccabees 13, 51.
The Jews entered it, the citadel of Jerusalem, with praise and palm branches
because a great enemy had been crushed and removed from Israel.
2nd Maccabees 10, 7.
Carrying ivy wreaths, wands, and beautiful branches, and fronds of palm,
they offered hymns of thanksgiving to him who had given success to the purifying of the holy place.
That would be the temple.
If you are a history nerd, that's a really cool time in Israel's history of kind of siding with the Romans to kick the Greeks out.
It's got a lot of history there if you're interested in that.
I just wanted to give that piece.
I'm going to get back on now.
The only recorded use of palms in celebration for the Israelites was this.
One, liberation of the Israelites in battle.
They won the battle.
God gave them the victory.
And two, cleansing the temple.
So we see Jesus cleansing the temple, right?
But where's the liberation?
Where is the call to arms?
Where is the army at the back of the king?
Is it possible that in laying down of palm leaves as part of the celebration of welcoming Jesus into Jerusalem,
that the people were also signifying what their prophetic expectation was of Jesus and what they expected him to do?
See, indeed, the prophesied Messiah had come, and he had come as the glory of God from the east and into the temple.
Matthew 21, 12 records,
Jesus went into the temple and threw out all those buying and selling,
and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the chairs of those selling doves.
And he said to them,
It is written, my house will be called a house of prayer, but you are making it a den of thieves.
See, Jesus has continually rebuked the chief priests as this returning glory of God
to cleanse the temple from the same thing that drove it away.
Corruption, rebellion, and idolatry.
Jesus then starts to heal the sick and the blind as a sign that the glory of God was present.
This is actually, if you're familiar with the Gospels,
this is actually the second cleansing of Jesus, of the temple by Jesus at Passover.
If you were to turn in your Bibles to John 2,
after the wedding of Cana, Jesus' inaugural miracle into ministry,
he then goes to Jerusalem and drives out the money changers and those selling animals with a whip.
When confronted by the Jews in verse 18, Jesus says this in verse 19,
Destroy this temple and in three days I will raise it up.
Then the Jews said, this temple took 46 years to build and you will raise it up in three days.
But he was speaking about the temple of his body, if you go on.
Jesus was of course not talking about the physical temple as his desire as God was never to abide in a building of stone,
but to abide with his creation as his temple.
Think back to Genesis, the garden, God dwelling among us.
Jesus was saying that here that the rededication and restoration of the temple will not be one of stone, but of flesh.
That Jesus came so that he can restore all that kept us from fully abiding with God and in himself.
All throughout the ministry of Jesus he abided with people.
He abided in Nazareth for 30 years.
He abided with his disciples both day and night.
He abided in the houses of Pharisees and tax collectors.
Because what Jesus is doing is calling us back to the reality of the garden where mankind abided with God.
See, the normal cultural context during the triumphant entry is to look for a warrior king, a victory, a restored kingdom, and a rededicated temple.
See, Israel sought a physical temple for God to dwell in.
But Jesus sought to dwell in man.
They expected a warrior king like David.
Instead, they received a suffering servant.
They expected a Messiah who would liberate them from the oppression of Rome.
Instead, they got a Savior who liberated them from the principalities of darkness that was behind the oppression of all of mankind.
They expected a war.
Instead, they got a leader who called his apprentices to wash feet and who died on a cross.
They expected the restoration of the glory of Israel.
Instead, they got the restoration of the glory of God to his whole creation.
Indeed, the ways of God can seem upside down to a man.
So also they seemed to the powers of evil and darkness.
So I read this quote while studying for this sermon.
I thought it was something deeply powerful in this conversation.
And it comes from James Stewart, who was the minister of the Church of Scotland.
It is a glorious, the quote goes like this.
It is a glorious phrase of the New Testament, that he led captivity captive.
The very triumph of his foes.
It means he used for their defeat.
He compelled their dark achievements to subserve his end, not theirs.
They nailed him to a tree, not knowing by that very act they were bringing the world to his feet.
They gave him a cross, not guessing that he would make it a throne.
They flung him outside the gates to die, not knowing that in that very moment they were lifting up all the gates of the universe to let the king of glory come in.
They thought to root out his doctrines, not understanding that they were implanting and perishable in the hearts of men the very name they sought to destroy.
They thought they had defeated God with his back to the wall, pinned and helpless and defeated.
They did not know that it was God himself who had tracked them down.
He did not conquer in spite of the dark mystery of evil.
He conquered through it.
Palm Sunday declares Jesus as king riding into Jerusalem.
The coming of the prince of peace, the coming of the glory of God, the son of David to reclaim his throne.
And the restoration of the true temple.
It just looked different than we expected.
I can't tell you what expectations are in your heart.
But I can ask you a series of questions and I know somebody who can tell you what the expectations of your heart are.
This Holy Week, are we welcoming Jesus as king into the temple of our bodies as a living sacrifice?
Will we be that place of abiding where heaven meets earth?
Are we ready to receive him into our city and the temples of our bodies, even if it looks different than we anticipated?
As the king comes, are we receiving him with shouts of hosanna, with a pure heart, or hidden motives?
When we think of victory, does it look like the cross?
Or would we rather have an army at our back?
Do we acknowledge the cross, but hold on to our own expectations of what victory looks like?
I'm going to get over here.
We may trust God to take care of us when we die, but do we trust God to tell us how to live?
Ways that may seem counter to our expectations, but he alone is God.
What expectations do we need to hand over to the king of the universe to repent from?
We're going to play a song.
It's a song you may have heard before, but it's something that strikes me in the very,
it vexes my flesh to the very person I am to hopefully conform me more into the image of Jesus.
But while that song plays, Pastor Ryan's going to come up afterwards and lead us in communion.
While that song plays, I want you to, hopefully you have a communion cup.
While that song plays, I want you to look at that cup, and I want you to reflect on it.
And I want you to think about the question that hits you the most,
or a question that you came up with, that you and the Spirit came up with.
And I want you to look at it, and I want you to reflect on who you are and who God is.
And for all my people on live stream, I'll have to cut you out,
but our tech team will have a song name and link come up on the song.
So I encourage you to reflect and do the same as us.
Take communion in your hand.
This is Christ's body broken for us.
I've got mine right here.
Christ's blood spilt for us.
Does this look like victory?
Or would we rather find victory in our own way,
rather than being radical disciples of the kingship of Jesus?
Search your heart.
Are there areas in your life that reflect your fleshly allegiance to something?
Your political allegiance?
Are there areas in your life that don't fully reflect allegiance to King Jesus,
and that because we're holding on to some expectation that we have placed on Jesus that he never promised?
Jesus isn't always the king we want,
but he's always the king we need.
Thank you, church.
Thank you.